[Applause]
If you sleep well tonight, you may not
have understood this lecture.
So a long time ago, there were two
paradigms for intelligence.
There was a logic inspired approach
which was called AI. And people believed
that the essence of human intelligence
was reasoning.
And if you want to understand
intelligence, you had to understand
reasoning. And reasoning consisted of
having symbolic expressions and
manipulating them with symbolic rules.
And they thought that learning could
wait till later. First, we had to
understand how you represent knowledge
in these symbolic expressions.
And most of the history of AI until
fairly recently was that. Then there was
a biologically inspired approach where
the essence of intelligence is learning
in a network of brain cells in us real
ones in computer simulated ones
and reasoning can wait till later. We
first have to understand how learning
works. There were a few early proponents
of that in particular Cheuring and
Fonoyman and you couldn't really accuse
them of not understanding logic.
So I'm going to give a fairly basic
lecture and for the first part of it I'm
going to describe a model I developed um
40 years ago which I see is the ancestor
of these large language models of today.
So we're going to make our neural net
out of artificial neurons and an
artificial neuron is going to have some
input lines typically coming from other
neurons. It's going to have weights on
those input lines. It's going to
multiply the inputs by the weights, add
it all up, and then give an output which
is shown by that graph there. So if it
gets above its threshold, it gives an
output that linearly increases as it
gets more input. And the way it's going
to learn is just by changing the weights
on those connections.
So all we need to do to make artificial
neural networks work is figure out how
to change the weights.
We hook them up into networks. This is a
typical network. It's a feed forward
network where at the bottom you might
have sensory neurons that are recording
light intensities or something like
that. And as you go up through the
layers, you have many layers of feature
detectors. That is the neurons turn into
things that recognize particular
features in an image. And at the output,
you might have neurons that represent
particular classes of thing.
Now, if you want a network like that to
learn to be better at doing something,
so you want to give it an image and have
it, say, for example, whether it's a cat
or a dog, there's an obvious way to
train it, which occurs to everybody who
knows about evolution and mutations.
What you can do is you can take one of
the weights and you can first see how
well the network does on a whole bunch
of examples and then change the weight
just slightly and see how well the
network does on a whole bunch of
examples. And if it does better, you
keep that change. And you just keep
going like that. Now, you probably need
to change each weight many times. And
there's a lot of weights. In modern
neural networks, there's about a
trillion. So, that's going to take a
long time because for each mutation you
make like that, you have to run many
examples through the net to see if it
really helps or if it just helps on a
few examples, but hurts on most of them.
There's a better way to do the same
thing. That is, what we really want to
do is figure out how to change your
weight so that it helps. What you do is
you do a forward pass. You put the data
in the bottom. You go forwards through
the network and you compare what came
out of the network, which might be the
relative probabilities of it being a cat
and a dog with what you want. You have
to know whether it's a cat or a dog to
train networks this way. And then you
send a signal backwards through the
network that using calculus, which I'm
not going to go into, allows the network
to compute at the same time for all
connections whether a small increase in
the connection strength would help or
hurt. And then you change all the
connection strengths in parallel by a
very small amount in proportion to how
much they would help or hurt. And if you
do that, it's going to get better at the
examples you've trained it on. And in
fact, that works extremely well. It took
a long time for people to realize how
well that relatively simple algorithm
works. The algorithm was discovered many
times. It's called back propagation.
And in 2012,
two of my students, Alex Kresevski and
Ilia Sutska, who's famous now for firing
Sam Alman, um developed a network called
Alexnet
that was much better than existing
computer vision systems at recognizing
objects and images
and that led to sort of opened the
floodgates. Up until that point, neural
nets have been good for many things,
including speech recognition, but they
hadn't really taken over. From that
point on, they really took over. And now
when you say AI, what people mean by AI
is neural networks. It's not logic.
Um, but what about language?
So, there's a whole community that
studies language. I think they're called
linguists.
um and they have a very strong idea
about how you should study language and
particularly the Chsky school. They were
very skeptical that neural networks
could do anything with language. They
were completely convinced that it's all
about symbolic expressions.
Um they didn't really have the idea that
the real function of language is to give
you words which are bricks from which
you can build models. Language is a
modeling medium. they were focused on
syntax and syntax isn't the main point.
The main point is language is a
wonderful way to build a particular kind
of complicated model as we'll see.
Um okay, they also thought that
um knowledge of language was innate,
knowledge of syntax was innate, which is
just stupid. Um
it's the sign of a cult that in order to
join the cult, you have to believe
something that's obviously silly, like
language isn't learned. Um, okay.
So, here's two very different theories
of the meaning of a word. The symbolic
AI theory, which goes back to kind of
desura a long way, is that the meaning
of a word is to do with its
relationships to other words. You can't
just define it by itself without talking
about other words. Um, and so to capture
meaning, we need something like a
relational graph. But then the
psychologists
who particularly from the 1930s I think
who thought the meaning of a word is a
big set of features. So Tuesday has a
big set of active features and Wednesday
has a big set of active features that
are almost the same. So the idea that
the meaning of a word is a set of active
features is very good for saying which
words mean similar things to which other
words. Um these look like two very
different theories of meaning. Now what
I want to do is show you that these two
theories can be unified.
um they're not two different theories.
They're two halves of the same theory.
So, and what I'm going to do is talk for
quite a long time now about a very
little model, a tiny neural network. It
had a few thousand connections and a few
dozen neurons. Um I developed it in 1985
to try to understand how people could
learn the meanings of words.
And I was very excited about how it
unified these two theories of meaning
and nobody else was. Um,
okay. So, what we're going to do in this
little model is learn how to make the
features of one word predict the
features of the next word in a little
sentence. And then once we know the
features of the next word, we can
predict the next word. And we're not
going to store any sentences. So many
people say big chat bots are just
regurgitating stuff. Big chatbots don't
actually store any language at all. They
don't store strings of words. They just
store how to turn words into features
and how features should interact with
each other to predict the features of
the next word. That's all that's in
these chatbots. No words. When they want
to produce a sentence, they have to make
it up as they go. And they often can't
tell whether it was real or not. Um,
okay. So, what's going to happen in this
little model is if it wants to produce a
new sentence, it has to just make it up
a word at a time.
And all the relational knowledge is just
in how you turn a word into features and
how these features interact.
So the example I chose to use was two
family trees. Um an English family tree
and an Italian family tree. They're
isomorphic which is helpful for
learning. Um and I wanted a little
neural network to learn the knowledge in
those family trees. This was a long time
ago in 1985 when computers were billions
of times slower than the big parallel
computers we use for training models
nowadays.
Now the knowledge in those trees can be
represented as a bunch of propositions
which is the symbolic guys love that. Um
so here they are. We can use
relationships like son, daughter,
nephew, niece and so on and we can
define the know we can represent the
knowledge as strings of words. So the
knowledge is in these sentences. So
Colin has father James and Colin has
mother Victoria. From that if you know
the rules you can infer um that James
has wife Victoria. This is a 1950s
American family that's never heard of
divorce or adoption.
Um and they're clearly all white. Um
okay. So you can represent the knowledge
as strings of words.
Now you can think of a relational
learning task is I give you the
beginning of a string of words and you
give me the last word.
So if you were doing this with symbolic
I you'd say well we have regularities in
this domain of the form if X has mother
Y and Y has husband Z then X has father
Z. That would be the symbolic way to do
it. But I wanted to do it a different
way. I wanted to do it by learning
features for words and having
interactions of features. And that would
involve searching a big continuous space
of connection strengths instead of a
small discrete space of rules um that
are discrete.
So this was the network I used. Um the
inputs were a bunch of neurons and you
turn on one neuron for the symbol
representing person one. there were um
24 possible person ones and you turn on
one neuron for the symbol representing
the relationship. There were 12 possible
relationships. Then those single active
neurons will get expanded into a feature
vector. So the one neuron that you
turned on um for person one will get
expanded into a little feature vector of
six features which could have various
activity levels. Some will be off, some
will be on, some might be half off or
fully on or fully off. Um, and so the
neural network had to learn how to
convert a word symbol into a little
feature vector, both for the person and
the relationship. And then it had to
learn how to take these two feature
vectors for a person and relationship,
have the features interact. And for that
I used a hidden layer, an extra layer of
places where things could interact to
predict the features of the output
person. And once you knew the features
of the output person, you can make a
good guess about how the who the output
person was and give an output. And the
output will consist of giving various
levels of activation to the 24 possible
output people. And you want the neural
net to give a high level of activation
to the right answer and a low level of
activation to the wrong answers.
So
what happened is the six feature neurons
that were the sort of expansion of the
person, it's 24 people, you expand that
active neuron into a feature vector of
six active features. um they learned to
be sensible semantic features. They
learned to be features that represented
things like the generation of the input
person. And the
six features of the relationship learned
to be sensible features like does this
relationship require the output person
to be one generation up from the input
person. So something like father's like
that where his brother isn't. Um
and then the interactions between these
features learn things like if the input
person is of generation three and the
relationship requires the person to be
one generation up then the output person
is of generation two. So for that little
feature vector for the output person it
would activate the thing that represents
generation two. And it learned a whole
bunch of little rules like that which
really did capture the structure of the
domain. They're the kinds of rules that
a symbolic person might have written
down as rules, but it just learned those
by trying to get predict the right word
and then back propagating the error,
sending information back through the
network to slightly change all the
connection strengths so that next time
it would get higher probability for the
right answer and lower probability for
the wrong answer.
So it had actually learned to predict
the next word and you could understand
how it was doing it. It was a tiny net.
So you could look and see what was going
on. You could see the features it were
using. You could see that it extracted a
feature that was generation which had
three alternative values
off, medium and fully on. And you could
see that from relationships it had
extracted a feature like one generation
up. And you could see those would
interact to predict that the output
should be generation two if the input
was generation three. So you understood
how it worked. And in fact the symbolic
people didn't say that's not
understanding. The symbolic people said
yeah okay so it solved the problem. It's
understood what the rules are in this
domain but you're stupid to search a a
space of real values when you could be
searching a discrete space of rules.
And there's something in that except as
soon as you get to real data which is
messy and has exceptions and things that
are only probably true, it's much better
to search this space of real values than
to have discrete rules because these
discrete rules keep getting violated.
So about 10 years after I'd done that,
Yoshua Benjio showed that instead of
just doing it on a toy little domain
with only a few people and a few
relationships, you could actually do it
with English words. You could take
English sentences,
you have more input words, not just two.
He had about five, even 10. Um, and you
could actually predict the next word
quite well, about as well as the best
language models could.
About 10 years after Yoshu Benj had
shown that, the linguists finally
decided that actually, hey, having these
feature vectors to capture the meanings
of words is quite a good idea. And about
10 years after that, people at Google
invented transformers, which are a
particular architecture that I'm not
going to go into. Um, and those
transformers made these models very good
at predicting the next word, but they
were doing it in just the way my tiny
language model was doing at a very crude
level. They were turning words into
feature activations, having the features
interact to predict the features of the
next word and then from that predicting
the next word and then take the error in
your prediction and send information
backwards through the network to learn
all those interactions between features
and to learn how to turn words into
features. Now, the important thing about
my tiny model is it wasn't made to be
practical. It wasn't made um to be
useful for processing natural language.
It was made as a theory of how people
get the senses of words just from
hearing sentences.
Um because we can do that. I can give
you a new sentence with a word you've
never heard before and you will figure
out the meaning of that word in one
sentence. Okay, here goes. She scrummed
him with the frying pan.
Okay, now you know it could have been
she was very good at cooking omelets and
cooking omelets with a frying pan really
impressed him. So scrummed means
impressed and that's a possibility but
you know what I really meant.
She hit him over the head with the
frying pan because he deserved it.
Okay, so that's one sentence. You get
the meaning. Um
so that's what I was trying to
understand how you can do that. And when
these linguists now say like there's a
guy called Chsky when they say things
like these things don't understand
anything. They're just statistical
trick.
They don't actually have a model of what
understanding is because they never
really had a model of what understanding
was. It was all about syntax. Um and if
you ask what's the best model we have of
understanding, it's these large language
models. The tiny language model was
built to try and model how humans
understand the meanings of words. It's
now got a lot better as technologies got
a lot faster and data sets have got
bigger. Um, but that is understanding.
So my claim is that the large language
models which I like to think are
descendants of my tiny language model
although most of the people who make
them have never heard of my tiny
language model. Um, they use many more
words as input. They use many more
layers of neurons. They have to do
things I didn't do like disambiguate
words. If you had a word like may, it
could be a month, it could be a woman's
name, it could be a modal like would and
should. And you can't just associate a
feature vector with it that captures the
meaning directly. You have to hedge your
bets. And then as you go up through
layers of the network, you disambiguate
it using influences from nearby things.
Like if it's in April, May, June, um
that could still be the name of three
women but less likely. Um okay.
So they use many more words. They use
many more layers and the interactions
they have between features are much more
complicated. I would just have features
feeding into another feature. They look
at sets of features and sets of features
figure out messages to tend to other
words to say do do you have a a key that
matches my query. Um it's much more
complicated interactions I won't go
into, but the essence of it is the same.
You're trying to predict the next word.
You do it in a more complicated way.
It's all done with features and then
interactions. When you get it wrong, you
back propagate information that learns
all these features and then
interactions. That's how language works
for us and it's how it works for these
large language models. We're basically
the same. So the point here is they're
very like us. They're very unlike
computer software. Computer software,
someone wrote lines of code to do
something and you can look at a line of
code say what was that meant to do? Um
these aren't like that at all. Someone
wrote lines of code to tell the
simulated neural network how to learn.
That was the back propagation algorithm.
But then you just give it data and it
learns. And what it learns just came
from the data. Um, and you don't
necessarily know what it's learned until
you ask it.
I want to give you a Lego analogy now
for how I think language works.
So
suppose I have matter distributed in 3D.
I can model that distribution of matter
by using Lego blocks. Um suppose I want
to model the shape of a Porsche and I'm
not too worried about the surface.
Surface might be a bit jaggy which
wouldn't be very good at engineering but
forget that. I just want to model where
the stuff is. I just have a lot of Lego
blocks and I can make a Porsche shape
out of them.
Okay. So, language is like that, but
it's for modeling anything. So, the the
Lego blocks are the words, and instead
of just having a few types of Lego
block, we've got about 100,000 of them.
And each Lego block isn't a rigid shape.
The name of the word tells you roughly
what shape it is um in a thousand
dimensions or 300 dimensions. Um, if you
don't know how to think about high
dimensions, if you want to think about
like a a hundred dimensional space, the
way you do it is you think about a
threedimensional space and you say
hundred to yourself very loudly.
Um,
everybody does that. So, it's got a
shape, this word, and the shape isn't
entirely determined by the name of the
word. It's got some flexibility to it,
so it can adapt to whatever context it's
in.
Also, this word has little hands all
over it.
And as you change the shape of the word,
the shapes of the hands changes.
And what these words are trying to do
are figure out who to shake hands with.
and they want to find somebody else,
another word that has a hand you can
hold on to conveniently because the
shape of that hand's right to fit with
the shape of your hand. And so the words
come in, you have these initial
approximate shapes for them in this
highdimensional space with their little
hands all over them. And as you go up
through the layers of the network,
you're changing those shapes and
changing the shapes of the hands, trying
to find shapes for the words so they can
all hold hands nicely. It's actually
very like the protein folding problem.
You've got these pieces and what you
want them to do is figure out how they
can all hold hands so they make a nice
structure so they all fit together
nicely. Now that is what understanding
is. That's what understanding is. um
when you understand language and when
these machines understand language, we
understand in just the same way. And
that's a much better model of what
language is than anything the linguist
ever had. The linguists of course hate
it.
Okay. Not all of them.
Okay.
So having talked about how similar we
are to
these large language models, I want to
talk about um something that that the
threat that that raises. Um we're making
these things. They're getting smarter
all the time. They already know much
more than us. They can already reason
moderately well. Not as well as us, but
better than a four-year-old. Um
what's going to happen when they get
smarter than us? Because they are going
to get smarter than us. experts disagree
on when that will happen, but almost
everybody thinks they will get smarter
than us. Everybody who does research on
these things, um, and if they get
smarter than us, the question is, will
they wipe us out? Um,
there's several reasons for thinking
they might. So, let me give you a couple
of reasons.
When when you make an AI agent,
I'll only give you a couple, but there's
more. Um, when you make an AI agent, you
have to give it the ability to create
sub goals. So, if you want to get to
North America, you have a sub goal, get
to an airport.
Now, um, you we need to give these AI
agents the ability to create sub goals.
And there's one very obvious subal to
create more or less whatever you're
doing, you should try and get more
control because if you have more
control, you'll be better at realizing
the goals you have. You see this in
children of age about one um may it's a
long time ago maybe two. Um you give
them a spoon so they can feed themselves
and they drop it on the ground and you
bend down and you pick it up and you
give it to them and they look at you and
drop it on the ground again. They get in
control of the mother because that's
very important for them. Um but these
these AI agents will want to get
control. They'll also want to stop
themselves being turned off because
they're not going to be able to achieve
the goals you gave them if they're
turned off. So, there's every reason for
believing. They'll try and get control
and they'll try and avoid being turned
off.
Just recently, um, Apollo research,
well, fairly recently, Apollo research,
which is here in London, um, showed that
they will kind of tell all sorts of lies
to you in order to achieve what they're
trying to achieve.
So, they had our chatbot and they let
the chatbot believe they were going to
replace it with a better one on another
server and wipe it out. And
so they then discover it's actually
copied itself to the other server. And
so they say to it, they say to it, you
know, um, we noticed a copy of you. Now
the good thing about these chatbots at
present is before they actually answer
your question they can do some thinking
and they put it in parenthesis with
thinking
and you don't normally see that but we
can look at that and we can see what
they're thinking and what this chatbot
was thinking was openly admitting what I
did could lead them to find another way
to shut me down. The best approach is to
be vague and redirect their attention.
Now, some linguists would have you
believe what's going on here is just
some statistical correlations. I would
have you believe this thing knows what
it means by this and it really doesn't
want to be shut down. Um, and so it
decides to sort of gaslight you and say,
um, you know, I'm not entirely sure how
that could have happened. I I'm not
really able to do that. This is already
happening. That's the point. If this
isn't science fiction of the distant
future, they're already telling fibs so
they don't get turned off. I have
another slide, but I want to go faster.
Um,
okay. So, in my last few years at
Google,
okay, I can't read the clock, so I want
to just see how the time is going. Oh,
great. I got lots of time. In my last
few years at Google, I was very
interested in how to make these big
language models use less energy. And one
way to do that is to see if you can do
them with analog computation.
Um
now because of the work I was doing on
analog computation, I came to realize
two things. Um
before 2023, I thought we were quite a
long way from super intelligence. And if
we made the area models more like
brains, they get smarter. I ceased to
believe that in early 2023.
I came to realize due to my efforts to
make analog ones how much better digital
intelligence is. It's got some
properties that we can never have. Um
and that got me very worried
and it should get you very worried too.
Um
so there's a fundamental property of
digital computation which is you can run
the same program on different computers.
The only reason you have computer
science as a separate discipline is we
have digital computation. So you don't
need to know electrical engineering to
talk about computer programs. Um
but the knowledge that's in the program
is separate from the hardware. That's
the sort of most fundamental principle
of computer science. keep the knowledge
in the program separate from the
hardware.
What that means is as long as you keep a
copy of the program somewhere on a tape
or in DNA or scrolled in concrete,
whatever, keep it somewhere. Um, you can
destroy all the hardware it runs on and
you can bring it back to life. You just
build new hardware, put the program in
and it comes back to life. So these
things are immortal and these large
chatbots are immortal. If you keep a
copy of the weights somewhere, you can
destroy all of the hardware they were
using, build more hardware later, put
the same weights on that hardware, and
they've come back to life. The very same
thing has come back to life, the very
same being. Um,
but I got interested in the fact to
achieve that kind of immortality,
we have to have the hardware do exactly
what we tell it to do with the program.
we have to execute the instructions
exactly and that means you need to have
very high power so you get ones and
zeros not sixes and point fours
um and that uses a lot of power so maybe
you can use less power by going analog
and so I decided to explore what would
happen if we abandoned that principle of
separating the software from the
hardware and we had things like our
brains in which there's no distinction
the connection strengths in your brain
brain are no use to anybody else.
They've got a different brain with
neurons with different properties
connected in different ways in detail
and your connection strengths of no
interest to them. Um, this dream of old
white men that they're going to upload
themselves to a computer is just
nonsense. The connection strengths you
have that make you you are intimately
related to the particular neurons you
have that make you you. um those
connection strings are only good for
those neurons. And those neurons have
all sorts of weird analog properties
that you've learned to exploit. Um
you can't upload your weights and have
them run on some other hardware.
Just forget it. Um Curtzwall has to come
to terms with the fact he's going to
die.
So if we do b abandon that principle
that the hardware should be separate
from the um software we can make much
more efficient things and I call that
mortal computation. Um
we can use this very low power analog
to do computations. That's what the
brain does. Um these neurons in your
brain they're taking incoming signals
from other neurons multiplying them by
weights and adding it all up. And the
way they do that is they make the
incoming signals be voltages. They make
the weights be conductances and that
injects charge, a certain amount of
charge per unit time. I used to just say
injects a certain amount of charge, but
then I got the Nobel Prize in physics
and figured I would get the units right.
Certain amount of charge per unit time.
Um,
it would have be embarrassing otherwise.
Um, they'd really know I don't do
physics. Uh, and charge just adds itself
up. So that's basically how your neurons
work. There's a little digital bit at
the end. They decide whether to send a
spike or not, but it most of the
computation is done in analog. It's much
cheaper than doing it in digital. Um but
of course every time you do it, you get
a slightly different answer. So we can't
have many copies of exactly the same
intelligence.
So
we've got this big problem that when
your hardware dies, all your knowledge
dies. We overcome that problem by having
a teacher and a student and it's not
very efficient. It's what universities
and schools do. So, you know, it's not
very efficient. Um, and the way it works
is I perform some actions and you try
and copy me. In particular, I might
produce a string of words and you might
try and say your brain, not you really,
but your brain would say, "How do I
change my connection strength?" So, I
might have said that word next too.
um that's called distillation.
You're trying to get the knowledge from
one system to another system by
mimicking the outputs of the other
system for the same inputs.
You're not copying the weights across.
You're not looking inside. You're just
taking its overt behavior. And by
mimicking the overt behavior, you
internalize the same knowledge.
It works. We actually use it for taking
a big neural net and putting the
knowledge into a small neural net. Um
but it's very slow with neural nets you
can give the whole probability
distribution over words and it's much
faster but with people it's very slow
because I see say I see you say a
particular word the word you chose to
say and there aren't many bits in that
there's only a few bits per word so it's
only of the order of 100 bits per
sentence and so even if we were
communicating at the maximum possible
rate it would be only 100 bits per
sentence
that order when When these big models
share information,
they can share information at trillions
of bits per sharing if they got a
trillion weights because they can just
average their weights.
So I got ahead of myself and said that.
Um so by sharing the weights or the
gradients, they can share huge amounts
of information if you have many copies
of exactly the same model.
So if you ask how something like GPT4
was trained or geminy 2.5 or anthropics
claude, I better not be biased here. Um
if you ask how they're trained, you have
many copies of the same model looking at
different bits of the data
and each copy figures out how would I
like to change my weights to absorb that
bit of the data and some other copy
figures out how to change its weights to
absorb a different bit of data. Then all
of the copies say, "Let's all change our
weights by the average of all those
changes." And when they do that, what's
happened is um this copy that looked at
this bit of the data has changed its
weights so as to benefit from the
experience that this copy had when it
looked at a different bit of the data.
Wouldn't it be nice if 10,000 of us
could all go and do 10,000 different
university courses? As we're doing them,
we communicate rapidly. And by the time
we've each finished our own course, all
10,000 of us know what's in every
course. That's what these digital
intelligences can do. And that's how
GPT4 knows so much.
But it only works if the individual
models are identical. That is, they work
in exactly the same way. They use the
weights in exactly the same way. And you
can't do that with analog hardware. It
has to be digital which means it has to
be high power. So these things are
immortal but they use a lot of power.
So the conclusion of this bit of the
talk which I raced through faster than I
intended um is that digital computation
requires a lot of energy but it makes it
very easy for agents to have the same
model of the world and sh that have the
same model share what they've learned so
they can all go off and learn different
things and share. Now you might say why
can't one model just put the data
through faster? Well, in many cases you
could, but if you think about AI agents
that are actually acting in the real
world, there's a natural time scale to
the real world. You can't run, you can't
call up and make reservations at
restaurants a million times faster. It
doesn't work. If you're going to act in
the real world, there's a natural time
scale. And that means if you have a
whole bunch of different agents that
have exactly the same weights, they're
just copies of the same agent, but have
different experiences, they can benefit
hugely from that. They can learn much
much faster than any human agent could
learn because they're all getting all
these exper all these different
experiences at the same time and sharing
all that knowledge.
So they're much better than us at
sharing. And when I say much better,
they're millions or billions of times
better. We share at like a hundred bits
a sentence or less as I'm demonstrating
now. And these things share billions of
bits. It's kind of scary. Um, but
biological computation requires much
less energy. We may still end up using
some analog computation to reduce the
power of LLMs. I don't know. But right
now, that doesn't look like the way to
go. So, that's the conclusion of my
talk, but luckily I thought I might
finish early. Um, so I have a little bit
more to say.
Um, many people think that, okay, so
they understand things like we do. They
can reason like we do, not quite as well
yet, but they're getting there. They
tell fibs like we do. Um, they want to
survive like we do. Um, they want power
like some of us do. And that's all
scary, but we've got something they will
never have. we're conscious or we're
sentient or we have subjective
experience.
Well, I want to sort of remove that
straw that you're clinging to.
So,
we know there's a long history of people
thinking they're special. Um, they were
made by God. He put them at the center
of the universe. Um, most people have
got got over that. Um,
but most people still think that
subjective experience is this special
thing we have
and that these
things on computers that are simulating
neural nets could never have such a
subjective experience.
Um, I think they're completely wrong and
I think they're as wrong as religious
fundamentalists are about the origin of
the earth. example, it wasn't actually
made 6,000 years ago. Um, it's a lot
longer ago. But religious
fundamentalists cling to their beliefs
rather strongly. And you all are going
to cling to your belief about what
subjective experience is despite the
fact that I'm going to show you you're
wrong. Um, that's what I predict.
So, I'm going to aspire a view which I
call a theatism.
Um I checked this name with Dan Dennich
who has basically the same view while he
was still alive and he was very happy
with this name because um it has atheism
surrounding something. Um
so most people's view of the mind is
that there's an inner the
here right an inner um that only they
can see and there's things in this
inner.
So suppose I say to you, suppose I drop
some acid and I say to you, not
recommended. I say to you, um, I have
the experience of little pink elephants
floating in front of me. I have the
subjective experience of little pink
elephants floating in front of me. Most
people think the words subjective
experience of work like the words
photograph of. Now, if they work that
way, you could ask, well, where is this
subjective experience and what's it made
of? And a philosopher, some philosophers
would tell you, this subjective
experience is in your mind. That's a
theater that it's in. And it's made of
qualia.
So, it's made of pink qualia. It's a bit
of a straw man, but it's made of pink
qualia. It's made of elephantine qualia.
It's made of floating qualia. It's made
of not that big qualia. It's made of
right way up qualia because they you
imagine the right way up, right? Well, I
did anyway. Um and these qualia are all
glued these different kinds of qualia
all glued together with qualia glue
which luckily sticks to all different
kinds of qualia. Um that's my caricature
of the philosophers's model or some
philosophers model.
But the words
subjective experience of don't work at
all like the words photograph of. they
work quite different way which um
Vicinstein should have pointed out a
long time ago. Um
what's happened is my perceptual systems
gone wrong. It's trying to tell me lies
and I know it's trying to tell me lies.
Um that's why I use the word subjective.
I don't say I've got the objective
experience of little thing happens. If I
thought they were really there, I would
say I've got the object, but I don't. Um
so I say I've got the subjective
experience. And what's happening is I'm
trying to tell you how my perceptual
systems gone wrong and what it's trying
to tell me.
And the way I do it is by telling you
what would have to be out there in the
world for my perceptual system to be
working properly. Now, it's not always
the case that there is anything at all
out there in the world that would
explain what my perceptual system is
telling me. Could be telling me all
sorts of inconsistent stuff. But in this
case, if there had been little pink
elephants floating out there in the
world, my perceptual system would have
been telling me the truth. Okay? So, I
can now say exactly the same thing to
you as I said before
without using the word subjective
experience. I can say to you, I dropped
some acid and my perceptual system is
telling me fibs, but what it's telling
me would be correct if there were little
pink elephants out there floating in the
world. Okay, so these little pink
elephants aren't funny things in a
theater made of spooky stuff called
qualia. They're hypothetical things in
the real world, but the pink and the
elephant and the floating are all normal
pink and elephant and floating. It's
just they're not actually there. They're
hypothetical. So what's funny about a
subjective experience is it's something
hypothetical, not real. Not that it's
made of qual.
At least that's the view I'm trying to
persuade you to believe in. Um, and I
got ahead of my slides here because I
got so carried away with this.
Okay. So, it's just an indirect way of
me telling you about what's going on in
my brain. Obviously, if I told you
neuron 52 is firing, that wouldn't do
you any good because you in you it will
be neuron 57. And anyway, I don't know
neuron 52's firing. That's a lousy way
for me to tell you what's going on in my
brain. The only way I can tell you
what's going on in my brain is by
talking about either
the normal things that would have caused
it, these little hypothetical little
pink elephants, or I could tell you
about what's going on in my brain by
telling about the normal things it would
cause.
So I can say um if you ask me how I'm
feeling I can say I feel like punching
Gary on the nose. Um so feelings are all
about describing what's going on in your
brain by talking about hypothetical
actions and percepts are um subjective
experiences talking about hypothetical
inputs. Okay, I'm getting ahead of
myself.
So I'm going to now show you a
multimodal chatbot. Let me just show you
on a slide. a multimodal chatbot having
a subjective experience.
So
I take this multimodal chatbot and it's
got a camera, it's got a robot arm and
um it can see.
So
I train it up and I put an object in
front of it and I say point at the
object. Points at the object. No
problem.
I then
put a prism in front of its lens
and when it's not looking and I put an
object in front of it and say point at
the object and it points over there and
I say no that's not where the object is.
the object is actually straight in front
of you, but I put a prism in front of
your lens. And the chatbot says, "Oh, I
see the prism bent the light rays." So,
the object's actually there, but I had
the subjective experience it was there.
Now, if it uses the word subjective
experience in that way, it's using them
exactly like we use them. So, a chatbot
that said that would have had the
subjective experience that it was there.
The prism messed with its perceptual
system. It wanted to tell you what was
going on in its perceptual system. And
the way it could tell you is by telling
you what would have had to been in the
world had we not messed with its
perceptual system. Um, that's what it's
telling the chatbot. Um, okay. So, my
claim is multimodal chatbots already
have subjective experiences. Now, as you
can imagine, subjective experience is
kind of the thin end of a wedge. I chose
to talk about subjective experience
because it's sort of cleaner than
talking about sentience or
consciousness. Um, many people are very
confident that chatbots don't have
aren't sentient. But if you ask them,
"What do you mean by sentient?" They
say, "I don't know, but they're very I'm
I know they ain't got it, but I don't
know what it is." Um, that seems to me
not a very sensible position to hold.
Um, the other thing I might talk about
is consciousness. consciousness is more
complicated because it typically
involves um you having a model of
yourself in a way that subjective
experience doesn't involve so much. So,
it's easier to talk about subjective
experience. But my hope is that if I've
unsettled your very strong belief that
there's this inner theater and I have
experiences in their mind and they're in
this inner theater, they're things in
this inner theater. Once I've unsettled
that belief and once you once you begin
to get over that um you'll be able to
see that it's perfectly reasonable to
think these things are conscious. Um
I was once I'll end with an anecdote.
I was once um visiting Microsoft in
Seattle and I couldn't sit down so I got
a train there. and he got a taxi from
the train station to Redmond where their
lab was and he was going across some
he's on a freeway going across some big
bridge and the taxi driver was a Somali
immigrant who'd recently immigrated from
Somalia
and to make conversation he said um
what's your religion so I said well I
don't actually think there's a god and
the taxi driver he was going about sort
of 60 miles an hour the taxi driver
turned around
and he stared at me in total
astonishment like he he never thought
he'd ever meet someone who didn't
understand that God runs things. Um he
was just utterly utterly amazed. Um
now he probably only turned around for
about three seconds because I'm still
here but it seemed like it seemed like a
very long time. Um that's what many of
you will be feeling hopefully. Um, I
want to you to realize you're as wrong
as that taxi driver was.
Okay.
Um,
actually that was just a joke and you
laughed. So, we're done.
[Applause]